בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is דף למד Daf Lamed
and we pick up at the top of כט עמוד ב, Kaf-Tet
Amud Bet, two very quick just comments about yesterday. Number one is
I did a little research about the whole רש"י's Rashi commentary on
בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. So first of all, the point is it's
not like he has three versions, it's more the assumption is he
basically just edited his basic commentary throughout his life, not an official
multiple version. In terms of as בבא בתרא's Bava Batra concerned,
the רשב"ם Rashbam in a few places explicitly references that he had
some of רש"י's Rashi commentary or some notes essentially of רש"י Rashi
on the that he was incorporating on בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. So
that's interesting. But in terms of any evidence about whether he actually
wrote a commentary on the rest of בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, we
don't have any direct evidence. What we do know is that he
had obviously some basic notes at least or whatever or some draft
of it that the רשב"ם Rashbam drew on. What is interesting, and
I saw that Grossman tries to claim, oh of course, how could
רש"י Rashi not have written a commentary on בבא בתרא? Bava Batra?
It must be that it got lost, etc. But if it got
lost then the interesting thing is that תוספות Tosafot from this point
on always references
רשב"ם. Rashbam. And whenever he references רש"י Rashi it's what רש"י Rashi
says in another מסכת. Masechet. So it's not... if it got lost,
it got lost very quickly is all I'm going to say. It's
not like it got lost three centuries later to the printers. So
it is interesting question. There is no real direct evidence and if
anything the implication is the absence of רש"י Rashi being quoted in
תוספות Tosafot that he didn't write the commentary. Yeah, I don't know,
whatever. Everything is a lot of speculation. The other thing I wanted
to say is we ended yesterday by this issue about that it
has to be it can't be discontinuous the חזקה, Chazaka, which led
to an understanding or at least a questioning in the גמרא Gemara
that maybe you need direct testimony that somebody is there constantly, or
can it just be assumed that if you say, look, we saw
the guy in the house or whatever, without evidence to the contrary
you assume it means night and day and so on. So תוספות
Tosafot read more as you assume it. The רשב"ם, Rashbam, that's the
conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. The רשב"ם Rashbam read it more that
you need the direct testimony and mentioned to you that the רשב"ם
Rashbam somewhere said that it had to be every single day and
I actually found that, that's the רשב"ם Rashbam here on כט עמוד
ב. Kaf-Tet Amud Bet. So if you just take a look at
the רשב"ם Rashbam on כט עמוד ב Kaf-Tet Amud Bet he says,
about one two three four five six seven eight nine ten lines
down, or nine lines down in the narrow lines, he says: הלכך
יביא המחזיק עדים שלא יצא מן הבית כל שלוש שנים אפילו לילה
אחת. Hilkach yavi hamachazik eidim shelo yatza min habayit kol shalosh shanim
afilu layla achat.
So I mean I don't know, your house has to be a
prison or something. But anyway but according the one sort of concession
the רשב"ם Rashbam makes is that if the guy doesn't demand, claim
that he knows you were absent or and demand that you testify,
then you don't have to. But if the guy is smart enough
to demand it and there's a question does he have to actually
claim I actually know that you weren't there? But anyway according to
the רשב"ם Rashbam you could certainly in some situations trigger an obligation
to testify that he was there every single day, which is every
single night. It's hard to prove and it's well right, like if
I'm buying a house or whatever and I want to stop holding
onto my שטר Shtar I can't leave for one night? Anyway it's
very strange. Let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay, ומודה רב
הונא, U'modeh Rav Huna, we're two lines from the top on כט
עמוד ב Kaf-Tet Amud Bet we're a little behind because we're getting
too interested in these things. ומודה רב הונא, U'modeh Rav Huna, now
רב הונא Rav Huna
who agreed that you have to be there night and day will
concede בחנותא דמחוזא b'chanuta d'Mechuza in the stores of מחוזא, Mechuza, דיממא
עבידי בליליא לא עבידי d'yimama avidi b'leilya lo avidi that those are
things that only happen in the day, they only have daytime hours,
they don't have nighttime hours. So those types of things that if
you say you bought a storefront or whatever that in those
cases... oh thank you. It's good today. Fine, perfect.
Okay that's fine. So you don't have to... what do you call
it? You don't have to be there day and night, you can
only be there in the daytime because that's what people... okay so
the question is is it what? Well is it three years of
daytime or is it six years? Right, is it sort of like
the fields that are laid fallow once a year? So you would
assume it means three years of daytime, the same way you don't
have to be working in your field in the winter when nobody
works, right? So תוספות Tosafot says well that would be true if
it was a standard storefront, a standard place that people only inhabited
in the day. But then he thinks that the גמרא Gemara wouldn't
be much of a חידוש. Chidush. So תוספות Tosafot actually thinks that
the case of the גמרא Gemara is that this is a place
where
sometimes it serves as residences and then it's day and night, and
sometimes it serves as a storefront and then it's only day, but
because for other people it serves as a residence, so on the
one hand you're allowed not to be there at night and that
doesn't create a discontinuity, that doesn't break the חזקה, Chazaka, but on
the other hand it's sort of like the fields that you lay
fallow, you need to be there a total of six years, six
years of day equals three years of day and night. I don't
know if that's פשט. Pshat. in the גמרא, Gemara, I think פשט
pshat in the גמרא Gemara is a type of place that you're
only there in the day, you know obviously you can be there
three years of daytime. All right, let's continue. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: We move on to another story. We really should
have read that yesterday.
I guess you can still use this studio and they live in
this studio.
Right, some type of a thing like that. Exactly. Okay, רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama and רב עוקבא בר חמא. Rav Ukva bar
Chama. Now we get into a story. רמי בר חמא Rami bar
Chama and רב עוקבא בר חמא, Rav Ukva bar Chama, so they
were apparently brothers. זבני הך אמתא בהדי הדדי. Zavin hacha amsa behadi
hadadi.
They bought a maidservant, a female slave in partnership. מר אשתמש בה
ראשונה שלישית וחמישית, Mar ishtamesh ba rishona shelishis vechamishis,
one used her the first, third, and fifth year. ומרי אשתמש בה
שנייה רביעית ושישית, Umari ishtamesh ba shniya revii veshishis, and the other
used her the second, the fourth, and the sixth year. נפיק עליה
לועא, Nafik ilei lua, so then somebody challenged and said, you know,
I never sold her to you, show me your שטר shtar and
so on, I was the original owner. Remember עבדים avadim are one
of the things for which you need a שטר shtar or חזקה.
chazaka. Years, years, years. אתו לקמיה דרבא, Atu lekamei deRava, came to
רבא. Rava. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
so he said to these two brothers, מאי טעמא עבידיתו הכי? mai
tama aviditu hachi? Why did you do this? Why didn't you, why
did you alternate years? Now maybe it's because they each needed her
service. But anyway, he says there's clearly a reason you did not
do it like a bigger block of time. It must be כי
היכי דלא תחזיקו אהדדי, ki heichi delo techziku hadadi, so you should
not have a claim against your brother and your partner and say
look, I was using it three years, you didn't object, clearly she's
all mine. So that's why you alternated it so there should not
be a continuous use of three years. So כי היכי דלדידכו לא
הוי חזקה, ki heichi delididhu lo havi chazaka,
the same way for
you, your alternative use of years did not serve as a חזקה
chazaka that you could claim ownership against your brother, so לא הוי
חזקה לאמה נמי לא הוי חזקה, lo havi chazaka le'ama nami lo
havi chazaka,
so neither of you has a חזקה chazaka towards the original owner
either. Nobody has a continuous three years. Now of course what you
would want to do is you would want them to be able
to be understood as a type of a unit like a corporation
and as שותפין shutfin they were using her continuously. So now the
גמרא Gemara is going to move on to that. So he says
והאמרו לא כתב איטרא. ve'amru lo kasav itra. Now all of this
is only if you did not write like איטרא itra here basically
means like a שטר שותפות. shtar shutfus. I don't know where it
means that but that's what it means. Okay. That or you know
a שטר shtar that identified the terms of your partnership that you
were going to alternate use of her from year to year.
So in that case אבל כתב איטרא קלא אית ליה. aval kasav
itra kala it la. But if you did then it has a
voice. Now what does this mean it has a voice? So רשב"ם
Rashbam has two explanations. One explanation is you write this שטר, shtar,
so me and my brother you know we bought
this עבד, eved, we write a שטר, shtar, so maybe we don't
even need three years of חזקה, chazaka, because maybe we can say
to the original owner, hey you heard that we processed in court
a שטר shtar that basically defined the parameters of our partnership about
this slave. If we hadn't bought her from you, you should have
objected. So that almost becomes a parallel provocation to three years of
חזקה. chazaka.
Okay, the שטר shtar was for but that was the terms of
partnership.
Yes, but the שטר shtar is making an implicit claim that she's
ours. So one, it's an extreme read, the רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't like
that. But he suggests that some want to say that the very
writing of the שטר shtar that implicitly is expressing our ownership and
defining the terms of our partnership should have served as sufficient provocation,
right, and if not then your silence immediately we have a חזקה.
chazaka. But he's much more, he doesn't like that. He much more
prefers the idea that that therefore like frames the nature of our
partnership and therefore you when you, because you the original owner and
you're coming and saying I didn't bother to protest, you weren't using
her consistently, that was not enough of a way of demonstrating ownership
that I felt I had to say something. Right, remember it's all
interconnected, the way that three years makes a statement of you as
the owner
gives the original owner a provocation you know sufficient provocation to say
something. So now he can't say that because you could say back
to no there was an official documentation that people knew about, that's
the קלא אית ליה, kala it lei, that framed this as a
partnership. So therefore as partners we were being מחזיק machzik in her
for three consecutive years and therefore you should have protested. You can't
say oh well nobody was actually demonstrating, our ownership of her was
framed in this way and therefore our חזקה chazaka is meaningful. So
that's the better way that the רשב"ם Rashbam prefers to read this.
Okay.
But you'd have to have this איטרא שטר itra shtar available. Right?
Like would it actually still have to be extant, this שטר איטרא?
shtar itra? Yeah.
Well that's an interesting point. I mean if people could testify that
they remembered it, that's an interesting question. Maybe, maybe not. But you
need enough evidence that it makes the claim that we were operating
as partners. Okay. Okay, so then he says like
this. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. And we're going to see this later
on that there could be cases where different people use the field
but if there's enough evidence to frame it as some type of
a you know joint participation then that can serve as then that
can serve as חזקה chazakah as sufficient provocation. Yeah we'll see we'll
see cases. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So it
says like this. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אכלה כולה חוץ מבית רובע.
achlah kullah chutz mibeit rova.
Now you there are operating on the assumption now we're going to
sort of shift more to just context questions about like the physical
ground here, not more the conceptual חזקה. chazakah. You're there you're working
the whole thing but you left over a little corner of the
field, a בית רובע. beit rova. בית רובע Beit rova was, oh
that was that classic thing that was I think a 50 אמה
amah by 50 אמה, amah, right? Was that what that was? I
think so. What?
It's approximately 104 square אמות. amos.
104. Oh I'm sorry I was confusing it with a בית סאה.
beit se'ah. I'm sorry. Okay so 104 square אמות. amos. That's pretty
small. That's like 10 אמה amah by 10 אמה. amah. Like 15
feet by 15 feet. That's very small. Okay so you worked the
whole field and you left over a tiny little square, okay, בית
רובע. beit rova. So קנה כולה חוץ מבית רובע. kanah kullah chutz
mibeit rova. So you so the same way we were talking before
that you whether you can interpolate the evenings without direct testimony of
the evening, right here it's not just it's not the absence of
testimony but it's the fact that you left over this corner. So
your חזקה chazakah on the entire field doesn't implicitly you don't look
and say oh we're going to look at the whole field as
an indivisible unit. No, you only used 99% of it, so you
only have proof for 99% of it. That 1% you didn't use
you don't have proof. Okay? Maybe he sold you 99% and he
left over this little corner for himself. Okay? So you didn't use
it and you didn't provide a provocation for that
corner. So קנה כולה חוץ מבית רובע. kanah kullah chutz mibeit rova.
It's an interesting phrase by the word קנה, kanah, right? But anyway,
because it's more about evidence, but anyway, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע: Amar Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua: ולא אמרן אלא דבר זריעה
היא. v'lo amran ela de'bar zriah hi. That's only if it's a
place that could have been planted. אבל לאו בר זריעה היא, aval
lav bar zriah hi, if it's not a place that could have
been planted, קני לה אגב ארעא. kani lah agav ara. So since
that you have evidence of the whole thing and there was no
reasonable reason you shouldn't have planted this, it was too hard, it
was rocky, whatever it was, so we presume that that's all part
of the same plot of land and your
חזקה chazakah on the rest of the plot works for this. So
the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב דימי בר אביי matkif lah
Rav Dimi bar Abaye רב ביבי בר אביי Rav Bibi bar Abaye
challenged this. And he said אלא מעתה צונמא במאי יקני. ela me'ata
tsunma be'mai yikni. Let's say you bought a rock. You bought like
a you know a place that was totally hard rock. There was
no way to plant. How would you be able to do a
חזקה chazakah on that? אלא באוקמי בה חיותא ומישטח בה פירי. ela
be'okmi bah chayuta u'mishtacha bah peiri.
There's other ways you use something if you can't plant. If you
had a whole plot of land that wasn't plantable, you would show
your חזקה chazakah by having your animals you know quartered there or
you know spreading out your fruit to dry in the sun. There's
ways of using something without growing. הכא נמי באוקמי בה חיותא אי
נמי מישטח בה פירי. hacha nami be'okmi bah chayuta i nami mishtacha
bah peiri. You can't say oh I couldn't have used it. There
were ways you could use it. So since there are ways you
could have used it by having your animals there or the fruit
or whatever and you didn't, so it's an absence of a חזקה.
chazakah. Now of course the difference is is there it's a whole
plot. So you know here you're basically saying can we reasonably assume
that your חזקה chazakah on everything else shows that you bought the
whole plot of land? Right? Especially and it's not under it's not
easily usable. I'm basically growing wheat then I'm going to use this
little square here to be drying out fruit or putting some animal
there, right? So it does raise that obviously question. You know before
we had the גמרא Gemara discussing reasonable. Ah you expect me to
watch to work my land when everybody else is letting their land
lie fallow? Right? So it is very interesting here about like okay
but like you know it's the reasonable assumption is that he bought
the whole thing. I do wonder the phrase קני kani you acquire
because that does echo I mean it could be being used loosely
of course but that echoes back that earlier idea that you know
חזקה chazakah maybe creates ownership rather than proves ownership. So if you
think about it as creating ownership then you could say well you
never did a קניין kinyan on this little piece. You know you
never did something that transferred status of this little piece. So that's
if you think about it along those lines but we like to
rather think about it as evidence rather than as creating something.
He just fenced the area? Oh.
Let's say he fenced
it but didn't use it.
Yeah so that's a good point you know that's what Michael asked
before. It's actually the what constitutes חזקה chazakah for three years is
actually somewhat of the converse of what creates חזקה chazakah as an
act of קניין. kinyan. What creates חזקה chazakah as an act of
קניין kinyan is doing something to the land that is about taking
care of the land right building a fence. What creates חזקה chazakah
for a three year is deriving benefits from it because that's the
provocation for the original owner right because if you just built a
fence around my land I could say yeah you want to come
and build fence around my land like why should I complain? Right?
So anyway obviously there are times where when it's in a larger
context and that's what's here sort of you know the argument how
much do we look at the larger context? חנה Chana by the
way I don't know if people got a chance to see I
didn't get a chance to see but apparently sent out a Wikipedia
article on what's it called adverse possession which is like exactly this
you're taking possession of something and it also like requires it's a
טענה ta'anah it has to be public it has to be sufficient
provocation so very sort of basically the same
idea. But not denying the owner access.
I mean, he didn't want access. And how much are you using
it for yourself?
So, it's
okay, let's say I fenced the whole thing and I use 99%
of it. So no one would reasonably say, yeah, that means I'm
really not, you know, using the other 1% has provoked you on
the whole thing, I mean.
Right, well that's the question. Is it that we're making an argument
like, you know, maybe he sold
99%? How, why should we assume he sold 100%? You don't have
a שטר. shtar. Right, so maybe it's that argument. Yes, it's bizarre,
but there's no, on the other hand, you don't have a שטר
shtar and there's no direct evidence, there's nothing really to prove that
he sold that other 1%
even though I fenced it and did the rest.
Right, I do think the words, the phrase קני kani in this
context suggests the other more first idea, which is the more magic
idea, whatever it is, you
know, it's not evidence, it's just, well I'm here, I'm acting as
owner, that makes it mine. So you think act as owner on
this little piece. Okay, let's move on. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ההוא דאמר ליה
לחבריה. Hahu de'amar lei lechavreih. Somebody said to his friend, מאי בעית
בהאי ביתא? Mai ba'it behai beita? This is great. We're going to
have a whole series of cases like this. Somebody said, what are
you doing in my house? What are you doing in my field?
And then we get to get to the response and we get
to all these cases that are debated. מאי בעית? Mai ba'it? And
by the way, what I should also say, which is much less
common, you know, in and we shouldn't take it for granted, is
case law in the
גמרא. Gemara. Scholars have a whole question when the גמרא Gemara was
being written, right, obviously you had the rabbis and their students who
were totally invested in this whole thing. But how much were the
common people totally bought in that these were the laws that governed,
particularly if you want to sort of talk about like their civil
laws, you know, not their ritual laws. So it is very interesting
to actually, scholars look at how often you have actual cases recorded
in the גמרא. Gemara. And sometimes it's disproportionate in certain areas over
other areas. Okay, but anyway here we get a lot of cases.
Now a question of course becomes how much
are these real cases or are these illustrations? Right, some of these
sound a little more like illustrations than real cases. But anyway, let's
take a look. Okay, so ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה. Hahu de'amar lei
lechavreih. Somebody said to his friend, מאי בעית בהאי ביתא? Mai ba'it
behai beita? What are you doing in my house? אמר ליה מינך
זבינתה ואכלתי שני חזקה. Amar lei minach zevintah va'achalti shenei chazakah. I
bought it from you and I've had three years now that I've
been here. Okay, שני shenei means שנים shanim של shel years. אמר
ליה אנא בשכוני גואי הואי. Amar lei ana beshikunei gavai havai. I
was living in the inner chamber of the house, you know, and
therefore what? So somebody had mentioned this before, meaning the claim here
is, and the way תוספות Tosafot says is that I can bring
evidence, it's not just סתם stam a claim, I can bring evidence
you owned the front of the house, I can bring evidence that
I was living in the back of the house. So what? So
my claim is, here's the question, was I going in and out
of the back of the house from the back door and therefore
you know then you could have bought the front of the house
and I wouldn't have known or was during the course of the
three years I was going through the front of the house and
constantly showing my presence there and therefore that made it clear that
you weren't the owner because I was, you know, maybe you were
a renter, maybe I was lending it to you.
Nobody knows what he's doing.
Yeah, that is a good point. That is a good point. What
are you doing claiming it's yours I guess you know. Maybe he
was a guest who overstayed his welcome and he said what are
you still doing here after
three years? Right, right. You know it's what's the name, Jackie Mason
has that line, you know the line he says he says that
gentiles leave without saying goodbye, Jews say goodbye they never leave. Yes,
Rabbi Dov. I wanted to ask on the structure of this. אמר
ליה מינך זבינתה
Amar
lei
minach zevintah
is the guy who was found in the house. Right, right. Then
אמר ליה אנא בשכוני גואי הואי, Amar lei ana beshikunei gavai havai,
the owner now says too, right?
The owner now says, the owner now says, I was living in
the back
room, the owner is saying back to him,
back to him, I was in the back room and I was
constantly using my house, it was my house, you were maybe you
know being renting it or something.
The squatter is the guy who should have been hiding in the
back.
Well right, anyway also came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So here
it sounds like it was a real case. They came to רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר ליה זיל ברור אכילתך. Amar lei zil baror
achilatcha. Go prove your consumption. Meaning you the guy who is the
מחזיק, machzik, prove that you used it in exclusion, like you know
sort of by yourself, that he wasn't present. Now first of all
it's a little hard to prove an absence, okay, but no, but
if somebody is testifying that I saw the guy living in the
house, you know, you could sort of have them testify, you know,
this other guy is claiming that he was there, what did it
look like to you? Did you see this other guy around and
present? תוספות Tosafot says the only need for him to now the
burden to shift, that he would now have to clarify is that
this guy is bringing evidence that he actually had been living in
the back room. Now that's not clear in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Part of the ongoing question in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to directly get to, is who has the
burden of proof? Okay, so what תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* introduces is that
this guy proves he was in the back room and that created
now the responsibility of the other guy to prove that he had
not been a constant and ongoing presence, this other guy, the original
owner. זה בור אכילתך *Zeh bor achilatcha*. אמר ליה Amar leh רבא
לרב נחמן *Amar lei Rava leRav Nachman*, so רבא *Rava* said to
רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*, הכי דינא? *Hachi dina?* That's the law? המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi me-chavero alav hara'ayah. *Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah*. If
the one who's coming to take it away has the burden of
proof. Now, here's very interesting. Who is the מוציא *motzi*? So this
is what I sort of wrote up on the board of option
number three. What רבא *Rava* assumes is once you prove that you
were there for three years, you're the מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak*. You're the
possessor, not necessarily the owner, but it's considered to be under your
possession, okay, under your control. And if the guy wants to, the
original owner wants to say that he's still the owner, he has
the burden of proof. He's the מוציא *motzi*. So it's not direct
evidence that it's yours yet, necessarily, but it at least creates a
status of מוחזקות muchzakut *muchzakut*. You are the sort of, you're the
one in physical control and if he wants to claim it's his,
he has the burden of proof. So now what רבא *Rava* option
number one is, I don't know that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* develops
this, but certainly one thing implicit in the three years is it
makes you the, you know, you the one who's possessing and shifts
the burden of proof to the other person, okay? Now maybe that's
all it does. Once the other guy has the burden of proof,
you don't have to directly prove it's yours, you know? And maybe
that's the entire way חזקה chazakah. *chazakah* works, but it's certainly a
piece of חזקה chazakah *chazakah* for רבא *Rava*. And what comes out
here as well is that even when now,
even when a question is raised, a challenge is raised, apparently since
right now, as far as we know, you had it alone, even
though now the person is raising a reason to be questioned whether
he was present, that still, that still doesn't undermine your basic status
as מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak*. And he still is the one with the
burden of proof. Okay, so that's what רבא *Rava* says. Yeah, it's
very nice that you were in the inner house, but we don't,
but we still have testimony he was here, we don't have direct
evidence that you were present in that space, so you still have,
you, the original owner, still have the burden of proof. המוציא מחבירו
hamotzi me-chavero. עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah*.
Yeah, he says on the front of the house or on the
whole house?
No, on the front, on the part where he was מוחזק muchzak?
*muchzak*. It's sort of like the previous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Like if
a little square land you're not מוחזק muchzak *muchzak* and you're not
מוחזק muchzak *muchzak* in the back house. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, so now we seem to have this question
of is the original owner the מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak* or the current
possessor the מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak*? רמי דרב נחמן אדרב נחמן, רמי דרבא
אדרבא, רמי דרב נחמן אדרב נחמן *Rami deRav Nachman a-deRav Nachman, rami
deRava a-deRava, rami deRav Nachman a-deRav Nachman*. Now רבא *Rava* and רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* seem to have reversed their positions in the following
case. דההוא *De-hahu*, no,
we're not going to say that. We're going to say a more
interesting answer. דאמר ליה לחבריה *De-amar lei le-chavrei*, top of ל"א ע"א
*Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph*, somebody said to his friend, כל נכסי דבי
בר סיסן מזבנינא לך *Kol nichsei devei Bar Sissan mazbinna lach*.
I'm going to sell you all of the property of דבי בר
סיסן *Devei Bar Sissan*, the house of Bar Sissan. Now the רשב"ם
Rashbam *Rashbam* explains, obviously sometimes all the details are, you know, the
devil's in the details and they're not always explained, but what the
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says is it sounds from this case that I
basically say to Michael, "Michael, I just got through this big transaction
with...
right, right. You know that I bought the land from Bar Sissan,
all this land, and I'm going to sell the land of Bar
Sissan by implication means the stuff I bought from him. We'll see
why that's important. I'm going to sell it to you for a
hundred thousand dollars." You say, "Great," and we do it and we
record it and the whole thing. Now, of course, there's a little
bit of ambiguity. הוה ההיא ארעא דהוה מיקרי דבי בר סיסן *Havei
hahu ara de-havei mikrei devei Bar Sissan*. There was a land that
was called the land of Bar Sissan, and אמר ליה Amar lei,
האי לאו דבי בר סיסן היא *amar lei hai lav devei Bar
Sissan hi*. You know what? This actually was not, did not belong
to them. It was not part of that stuff I bought from
them. ויקרי הוא דמיקרי דבי בר סיסן *Veyikrei hu de-mikrei devei Bar
Sissan*. That's just what it was called. Maybe a hundred years ago
it belonged to them. But when I said I was selling it
to you... Now again, it's a little ambiguous. I said I was
selling you the דבי בר סיסן *Devei Bar Sissan* and we agreed
that that's what this is labeled, but somehow it's also understood that
what I meant was the stuff that I bought from דבי בר
סיסן *Devei Bar Sissan*. And I'm making the claim that this is
not among them, okay? But certainly looks like it, it's called it,
and I'm having all this other property. So what, who has the
burden of proof to prove whether it was or was not part
of that collection of property? אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן *Atu lekamei deRav
Nachman*. It came once again to רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. ואוקמה בידא
דלוקח *Ve-okmah beyada delokayach*. He said the purchaser can keep it because,
you know, prima facie it looks like it was part of the
collection that was sold. אמר ליה Amar lei, רבא *Amar lei Rava*,
so רבא *Rava* said, דינא הכי? *Dina hachi?* That's the law? המוציא
מחבירו hamotzi me-chavero עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah*. The guy, you're
trying to take it away from the seller. I'm the original owner,
you have the burden of proof. So go prove that this was
part of the portfolio of דבי בר סיסן *Devei Bar Sissan*. Now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it looks at least at the face
of it that we're reversing the position. Because here, if you don't
get too much into the specifics of the case, here רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman* says the purchaser is considered to be
the, you know, I'm sorry, let me make sure I got this
straight. Right, the purchaser is considered to be the owner, and Rava
says no, the purchaser is coming to take it away from the
מוחזקות muchzakut, of the original owner. So Rava here considers the original
owner to be the מוחזק. muchzak. In our case, it was the
reverse. Rava assumed that the guy who was there for three years
in the front of the house, who was not the original owner,
was the מוחזק. muchzak. So who's the מוחזק? muchzak. The seller or
the owner? Right? So in our case, Rava assumed that the מוחזק
muchzak was the buyer, and in this case, Rava assumed that the
מוחזק muchzak. is the seller. Now of course there's a big difference,
because in our case he had been there for three years. That's
what made him the מוחזק. muchzak, It's not just about buyer versus
seller, right? It's about where are you right now. So wait a
minute, let's see what the answer is. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, קשיא דרבא אדרבא קשיא דרב נחמן אדרב נחמן. kasha de-Rava ad-Rava,
kasha de-Rav Nachman ad-Rav Nachman.
So it looks like they're contradicting whether the buyer or the seller
is the מוחזק. muchzak, So the גמרא Gemara says, דרבא אדרבא לא
קשיא. de-Rava ad-Rava lo kashya. No, no, no, Rava isn't contradicting himself.
התם מוכר קאי בנכסי הכא לוקח קאי בנכסי. hatam mocher kay bi-nichsei
hacha lokeach kay bi-nichsei. Of course, that one answer is buyer or
seller, it's where are you right now. In our case, right, I'm
sorry, in the case over there by דבי בר סיסין, De-Bei Bar
Sisin, the seller was still essentially in possession. He had owned all
that land until now. We were doing a transaction right now. The
question was did this plot of land change hands right now? So
until this very minute I, let's make me the seller, was in
possession. So of course I'm the מוחזק. muchzak, You want to prove
it was part of the stuff I sold? You have to bring
the proof. I'm the מוחזק. muchzak? In the other case, the guy
has been living in the front of the house for three years.
That makes him a מוחזק. Okay? And if there's a question now
about that, that's the other person's responsibility. So that makes a lot
of sense. Again, the basic חידוש chidush about this is that three
years creates, you know, again it's a funny use of the word
חזקה. hazakah חזקה hazakah means a lot of different things. But anyway,
but here it means מוחזקות in the sense of I am the
one in possession. I haven't proved I owned it but I am
considered to be in physical possession and that creates the burden of
proof on the other. And even though what the other's challenge is
saying, that testimony that I am the מוחזק is missing a piece,
you know, there was some other part of that story that's not
being told, but you have to prove that. At least as far
as בית דין beis din knows, the story that's being told is
that I'm the מוחזק. One minute. So that's how to reconcile Rava.
Now how about Rav Nachman? What's going on with Rav Nachman? Okay,
so let's take a look. דרב נחמן אדרב נחמן נמי לא קשיא.
de-Rav Nachman ad-Rav Nachman nami lo kashya. Rav Nachman also isn't contradicting
himself. כיון דאמר ליה דבי בר סיסין ומקריא דבי בר סיסין אדידיה
רמיא ליה גלויי דלאו דבי בר סיסין היא. kevan de-amar lei De-Bei
Bar Sisan u-mekarya De-Bei Bar Sisan adidey ramya lei giluyei de-lav De-Bei
Bar Sisan hi.
Right, it's not a question we don't start necessarily with a question
about who's considered מוחזק, we start with a question about like what
does it seem to be that we've testified about? Right? Like so
who has the burden of proof based on like where the evidence
is? So you call it's called דבי בר סיסין, De-Bei Bar Sisin,
we all agree you sold the property of דבי בר סיסין, De-Bei
Bar Sisin, so the presumption is based on the facts, not based
on a status of מוחזקות, that it is דבי בר סיסין. De-Bei
Bar Sisin. So if you want to prove something, yeah, well, okay,
bring them to בית דין, beis din, maybe they do know, but
who has the burden to prove it one way or the other?
So the facts in evidence all indicate one way. The prima facie
read of the evidence is one way. You want to prove against
that, you want to make something that seems like counter-intuitive to what
sort of the evidence is showing, then that you have to the
person who's trying to prove something counter-intuitive to the evidence has the
burden of proof, not who's the מוחזק, which is very interesting, right?
Because we always assume the המוציא מחבירו. How much is המוציא מחבירו
balanced against a certain reasonable interpretation of the evidence? Let's say we
all agree that I'm the מוחזק, okay, and you go ahead and
you bring all this evidence that it's yours. And I come up
with some harebrained explanation how to reinterpret all of that evidence. At
what stage do we say you don't have to prove it anymore,
you know, that's considered proving it? My crazy explanation doesn't mean that
you now have to disprove some crazy interpretation. So that's what Rav
Nachman is saying is, he did prove it. It's called דבי בר
סיסין. De-Bei Bar Sisin. You want to give some crazy explanation? That's
not for him to prove, that's for you to prove. So yes,
he agrees to the idea of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. But the
question is what constitutes a ראיה? ra'ayah? Right? He did bring a
ראיה. ra'ayah. You want to say it doesn't prove it? You know,
that's a little far-fetched. You have to now explain that.
At least he brought a ראיה.
ra'ayah. This is called דבי בר סיסין. De-Bei Bar Sisin. Everybody knows.
You said you sold me the דבי בר סיסין, De-Bei Bar Sisin,
it's called דבי בר סיסין. De-Bei Bar Sisin. You want to say
oh no, that's just the name that it has, it's not what
it really means. Okay, so at what stage you're saying I brought
a ראיה. ra'ayah. Yeah, you want to have some crazy interpretation? You
go ahead, you know, I brought what normal people would consider a
ראיה. ra'ayah. So that's answer number one. Now how about back to
our other case? Why does he say the guy in the front
of the house is not considered a מוחזק? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אבל הכא לא יהא אלא
דנקיט שטרא. aval hacha lo yehei ela de-naki shtara. Let's say remember...
the idea of חזקה hazakah. *chazaka* is a substitute for a שטר
shtar *shtar*. So let's say I actually was living in the front
of the house and you said, what am I doing in the
house? I said, here's the שטר *shtar*, you sold it to me.
Okay, that's here's my חזקה hazakah. *chazaka*. What type of counter claim
could you have if I have a שטר *shtar*? To say? No,
that's not a counter claim I have a שטר *shtar*. מי לא
אמרינן ליה קיים שטרך וקום בנכסי *mi lo amreina lei kiyem shatracha
vekum binichsei*. We would say, validate the שטר *shtar*. Go show that
those are legitimate witnesses, a שטר *shtar* doesn't mean anything until the
עדים *eidam*. So here, I say I've got my three years and
you're saying, okay, but I'm raising even when you have the שטר
*shtar*, as it were, the חזקה hazakah *chazaka*, I could challenge it
and say that you have to prove that it's really saying what
it seems to be saying. Now, again, I don't know exactly it
doesn't fully explicate the difference because what type of a challenge is
a legitimate challenge, right? Like if, you know, if I can't say
בי בר סיסין *Be Bar Sisan* doesn't mean בי בר סיסין *Be
Bar Sisin*, why can't I say I was present there and you
have to disprove that? So obviously there has to be some judgment
call about how reasonable it is my counter claim. You know, and
again, that's why תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that in this case, I
have evidence that I was living in the back. So once I
have evidence that I was living in the back, and presumably it's
not crazy to try to prove, the same witnesses that say that
you were there for three years have them say that you were
there alone for three years. So again, in this case, it's considered
to be a reasonable challenge with something I assume that's reasonably disprovable.
So presumably that's why רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* says we accept that
and we demand, we don't say a חזקה hazakah. *chazaka* always ends
the conversation. You can raise questions, reasonable questions, which then have to
be clarified. Okay, does רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* deny the idea that
חזקה hazakah *chazaka* creates מוחזקות *muchzakut*? Again, for me, that's the more
interesting thing that emerges from this סוגיא *sugya*. That רבא *Rava* is
saying besides the חזקה hazakah. *chazaka* creates ownership, which is the first
idea, or that it's evidence of ownership, is that it creates a
sense of possession and it shifts the burden of proof. And it's
not clear whether רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* disagrees with that. It sounds
like he doesn't, but notice how רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* doesn't talk
about it in terms of חזקה Chazaka. *chazaka*. He says, okay, it's
a שטר *shtar*, but you can challenge a שטר *shtar*. So does
he actually, you know, accept or reject רבא *Rava*'s idea of מוחזקות
*muchzakut*? Right, that is not clear. Okay, there's a couple questions. We're
going to start with Charlie. Yes, Charlie. Yeah, I have a question.
I'm a little confused this בי בר סיסין *Be Bar Sisan*. Is
that what is called or what the actual or the actual בר
סיסין *Bar Sisin* was the actual owner?
So רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says
that
it's understood what I was telling you or what's left of the
בי בר סיסין *Be Bar Sisan* originally owned.
Originally owned.
And this is called בי בר סיסין *Be Bar Sisan* and we
all agree to that, but my claim is they never owned it
originally.
So בר סיסין *Bar Sisin* never owned it.
Exactly. And therefore it wasn't part of the portfolio that I agreed
I was selling to you.
Okay. All right. So it's not like it once was owned by
בר סיסין *Bar Sisin* but that was a hundred years ago and
people still call it.
Maybe, but it was not the concept of being owned by them
recently, which was the implicit understanding that we had.
Okay, got it. Yeah. So with respect to the first case, is
according to רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*,
are
you disproving the entire or are you disproving the back room?
No, apparently the back room was a fact as the way תוספות
*Tosafot* understands it. You're disproving that you were constantly present in the
front room in a way that would mean that my being there
for three years wasn't an act of חזקה Chazaka *chazaka*. If I
was in your property for three years
and you could bring evidence that you were regularly showing up and
walking around the property, it wouldn't be a חזקה Chazaka *chazaka* because
there'd be another interpretation: you're showing yourself as still the owner, right,
and maybe I'm there as a sharecropper, maybe I'm there as a
hired hand. So your ongoing presence...
the back door explanation because you've mentioned the possibility that maybe
it's like a back door. Right, exactly.
My
claim as the guy in the front of the house is not
that you weren't in the back room, but that you used the
back door, maybe every once in a while let you cut through
my room, my house, but basically you used the back door and
you were not having a presence in my half of the house
that would show that you were still the owner or... right?
But then what?
You're saying you... we all agree the way תוספות *Tosafot* frames it
that you still lived in the back and I lived in the
front. I said I bought the front, you said no, you were
a rental, guest or whatever. And your proof is that I was
regularly present there in the way that shows that I'm still the
owner. Okay, so now I have to prove no, you weren't regularly
present, you went in and out through the back door and you
did not basically demonstrate your presence in the...
So the point is that the implication of I was in the
back room is I was in the back room
and I was coming through... right, that's the point that's missing here.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay. Good? Alright, let's move on. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה
hu de-amlei le-havrei. *Ahu de’amar lei lechavrei*. Somebody said to his friend,
מאי בעית בהאי ביתא *mai ba’at behai beita*? What are you doing
in this my house? אמר ליה מינך זבינתיה ואכלתיה שני חזקה v'achaltiyah
shnei chazakah, *Amar lei minach zavinteih ve’achaltieh shnei chazaka*. I bought it
from you and I’ve been here for three years. אמר ליה בשכוני
בראי הויתי *Amar lei beshuchnei barai havaite*. It’s very parallel, בשכוני גואי
*beshuchnei gavai*. בשכוני גוואי, which is the inner dwelling place, and here
בשוקי ברא, be-shukei bara, the outer market, meaning
I was in a different country for three years. I was in
China in my business. That's I didn't know about it. Now here's
a really important update because maybe I was using some examples before
that were a little bit too dramatic.
If
you're in a country, a place that isn't actually a different country
that is not under the same
government, okay, then the person can't get a חזקה chazaka on your
land. They did not have telecommunications, okay. So if you are in
like one area of יהודה Yehuda and somebody is in a very
distant area of יהודה, Yehuda, that's חזקה שלא בפניו, hazakah shelo be-fanav,
which works because then word gets to you. But if you're in
יהודה Yehuda and the original owner is in גליל, Galil, then we
assume that there's not a lot of travel between those
places. Right, it's not that it's impossible, but there's not regular travel
between different regions and therefore חזקה chazaka, does not work. So that's
an important
clarification of the idea of חזקה שלא בפניו. hazakah shelo be-fanav. It
only works in regions where we assume a good amount of travel.
Alright, so this guy said I was in China the whole time,
I was outside of the country and therefore was a חזקה שלא
בפניו, hazakah shelo be-fanav, and therefore it doesn't work. Okay, so אמר
ליה אנא בשוקי ברא הואי. amlei ana be-shukei bara havei. I was
in some outside district. Okay. So אמר ליה והא אית לי סהדי
דכל שתא הוה אתי תלתין יומי. amlei ve-ha is lei sa'adi de-chol
shata havei asi tlasing yomei. Oh very nice, but I have witnesses
that every year you would come back for 30 days. So therefore
you could have found out about it during that 30 days and
you could have protested, so your silence is still evidence. אמר ליה
תלתין יומי בשוקא הוה טרידנא. amlei tlasing yomei be-shuka havei tridna.
No, those 30 days was when I was coming back with all
my stuff from China and I was selling them here. I was
too busy in business. So now there's an interesting question. Too busy
is the claim and I didn't hear I was so preoccupied with
business matters that I didn't hear that you were on my land.
Or that's the approach the רשב"ם Rashbam likes, or the רשב"ם Rashbam.
suggests but he doesn't like it, I heard you were on my
land but I was too preoccupied to do anything about it, to
make a מחאה. macha. And that's a weaker claim because making a
מחאה macha is just get two witnesses and say פלוני ploni is
on my land, I want you to know it's still mine, I
didn't sell it to him. So anyway רשב"ם Rashbam assumes that if
you admit that you actually heard about it you don't have a
legitimate claim you were too busy. But the argument is I was
too preoccupied I had no idea you were on my land. I
was here but I was too
preoccupied. Okay. אמר רבא עביד איניש דקאזיל תלתין יומי וטריד בשוקא. amar
Rava avid inish de-ka'azil tlasing yomei ve-tarid be-shuka.
That's a reasonable claim. People basically, you know, for 30 days could
be so preoccupied that it's a claim that he never knew about
it. Now again it's always interesting where's the burden of proof. By
the way, what I forgot to say, Michael left so he doesn't
get to hear you're always interested in the הלכה. halacha. While to
me Rava's approach before of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה ha-motzi me-havero alav
ha-rayah was the more attractive one, you know the רשב"ם says the
general assumption is הלכה כרב נחמן בדיני, halacha ke-Rav Nachman be-dinei, that
we actually went like Rav Nachman in the earlier discussion. But anyway,
but here there's an ongoing question of who has the burden of
proof, who has to clarify issues. Okay, so presumably the original owner
shows that he was in China. Okay, there's evidence that he was
back for a month each year. The original owner doesn't have to
prove like oh I'm going to bring witnesses that show that every
single spare minute I was busy in my business. I never went
to the movies I never went to anything you know I was
constantly. No, you don't have to prove it, you just have to
claim it. Right, once we know you were away even if we
know you're here but given the larger context that you're basically doing
business and so on, then that's a reasonable claim you don't have
to prove it and actually that undermines the person's חזקה. chazaka Yes.
You're talking about like sort of the idea of constructive notice. A
reasonable person in that situation should have known given the evidence the
guy is living there. Right, not actual knowledge.
Right, exactly. But now we've got right you never have to prove
whether you actually heard, but whether it was reasonable because of the
right. Now the other reason here that it might be a legitimate
claim is we start with the assumption that there wasn't חזקה. chazaka,
We start with evidence that the guy was not around for three
years. So it actually becomes a burden to prove that there is
חזקה chazaka, because you were here for a month each year that
creates חזקה. chazaka So you're a little bit starting without the presumption
of חזקה chazaka which might be part of what's going on here.
Alright, let's go to the next case. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה. Hahu
d'amar lei l'chavrei, Somebody said to his friend, מאי בעית בהאי ארעא?
mai ba'is be-hai ara? What are you doing in this land? אמר
ליה מפלניא זבנתיה דאמר לי דזבנה מינך. amlei mi-planya zavnisah de-amar li
de-zavnah minech. I bought it from פלניא Plonya who said to me
that he bought it from
you. Okay and now notice by the way that there is not
even years of חזקה. chazakah He doesn't say ואכלתי שני חזקה. ve-achalti
shenei hazakah. On the other hand also what we're going to see
in a minute is that the original owner doesn't have any evidence
that he was the original owner. So like everybody is lacking evidence
here. I don't have evidence that I've been here for three years,
you don't have evidence that you're the original owner, but what I
do say is I admit if I said I was always here,
I'd be believed. I mean, you don't have any evidence. But what
I say is no, I bought it from ראובן Reuven who says
he bought it from you. So אמר ליה he said to him,
את לאו קא
מודית
דהאי ארעא דידי היא, At lav ka modit dehai ara didi hi,
look, thank you very much! You have just admitted even though I
the original owner, let's have the people, ראובן Reuven I guess, I
don't know, שמעון Shimon is saying to this guy what are you
doing and he says I bought it from ראובן. Reuven. So now
שמעון Shimon is saying okay I bought it from ראובן Reuven who
said he bought it from you. You've just admitted that as far
as you know this land was originally mine. All right, so even
though I don't have proof that it's originally mine but thank you
very much you've just admitted that it was originally mine, דהאי ארעא
דידי היא, Dehai ara didi hi, ואת לא זבנתה מינאי Ve'at lo
zavinta minai and you're also not claiming that you bought it from
me. So in that case, זיל Zil get out of here, לאו
בעל דברים דידי את Lav baal devarim didi at you are not
my litigant, you are not making any direct claim against me and
you're conceding it's mine, so it's mine. So אמר רבא דינא קאמר
ליה Amar Rava, dina ka-amar lei, that's a good point and that's
a legitimate claim and the other guy loses. Now this is a
very terse case. What is really going on here? So I'll just
give you a little bit of what this big רשב״ם Rashbam is
about and I'll try to give you the basic issues. Let's start
in the following case. Okay let's take a more classic case. ראובן
Reuven it's known that it was originally ראובן's Reuven land. He comes
and he says to לוי Levi what are you doing on this
land? And לוי Levi says I've been here for three years. Okay
but he doesn't say I bought it from you ראובן. Reuven. He
says I've been here for three years and I bought it from
שמעון Shimon who says he bought it from you. Okay so now
it gets a little bit complicated because now he doesn't directly know
who owns it. But this is what he claims. So if he
had said obviously I bought it from you he'd be believed. If
he said I bought it from שמעון Shimon who I know bought
it from you because שמעון Shimon showed me the document or I
saw שמעון Shimon bought it from you he would also be believed
because of מיגו. Migo. The מיגו Migo is I could say that
I bought it straight from you so I'm believed to say I
bought it from שמעון Shimon and I know שמעון Shimon bought it
from you for whatever reason. But let's say he says I bought
it from שמעון Shimon and I don't know, he claims he bought
it from you, I don't have direct evidence, what would be the
story? So a later גמרא Gemara says that the story is that
I also win when I make that claim I bought it from
שמעון Shimon who says he bought it from you if שמעון Shimon
was there for one day, if at least we could prove evidence
that שמעון Shimon was there for one day. If there's no evidence
that שמעון Shimon lived on the land for even one day that
undermines any reasonableness of the claim that שמעון Shimon actually possessed it.
But once we have at least a little bit of evidence or
if I were to say not something that undermines completely undermines the
reasonableness of the claim then the point is like this: I was
here three years, why didn't you object? Somebody's on your adverse possession
on your land for three years you should object. So your silence
already becomes
whatever I'm claiming, you didn't know what I was going to claim
when we got to court, your silence during that three years already
becomes prima facie evidence that it's no longer yours. The only problem
here is that I say I bought it from ראובן Reuven and
I don't know that ראובן Reuven legitimately bought it from you I
just believe that he did. So the גמרא says well then we
make that claim on behalf of ראובן Reuven טענינן ללוקח Taninan lelokayach
and we sort of say that if ראובן Reuven were here ראובן
Reuven would say I bought it from you and I sold it
to שמעון. Shimon. And the proof that you're not still the owner
is you didn't say anything when שמעון Shimon was there for three
years. So even though I don't directly know it
we would provide that claim on behalf of ראובן Reuven since I
have the חזקה. chazakah, And the חזקה chazakah. becomes prima facie evidence
that you the original owner are no longer the owner. And the
גמרא has again this one qualification that ראובן Reuven had to be
there for one day. So that's in what I'd call a classic
case where you start with a knowledge of the original owner you
start with three years of חזקה chazakah but there's a middleman there.
And the middleman if I claim I know for sure then of
course it's fine. But even if I don't know for sure I
just say he said he sold it we would often step in
and make that argument on his behalf with the backup evidence of
the three years. David it looks like you want to ask something
about that.
Yeah I don't understand why we would need that one day for
ראובן. Reuven.
Yeah so the גמרא never spells it out but the ראשונים Rishonim
basically say that since we're making this claim, there is no direct
evidence of ראובן's Reuven ownership and we're making it on his
behalf, it's less than we need something to substantiate it it's more
like if he had never been on it at all it would
raise too many doubts like it would just be too suspicious. Okay
but it's not clear.
In three years and each,
no but it would be too suspicious that ראובן Reuven had never
actually bought it. But so what? If I'm some— if I'm ראובן
Reuven now, and I'm some charlatan and I come and I sell
it to you, right, and I never— and I never owned it,
so it could be that the owner's silence means that he's no
longer the owner, but your claim, if it turns out you bought
it from somebody who really was a charlatan, you're also not the
owner. It's a חזקה שאין עמה טענה. chazaka she'eini imah ta'anah. And
that's by the way, let me say actually say that because maybe
I need to re-emphasize and re-clarify that. Yes, you have three years,
and three years by itself should say, "Ah, silence in the face
of three years of adverse possession shows the guy isn't the original
owner." That's all very good, but it doesn't mean that it's mine
either, right? That's חזקה שאין עמה טענה. chazaka she'eini imah ta'anah. For
me to win, it has to be used to back up a
claim that's a legitimate claim that, you know, that's a legitimate claim
in court. So if my claim is, "I bought it from ראובן,
Reuven, who we all know is a charlatan and was selling me
property that wasn't his," then I also lose. Okay? And if I—
well, since and since nobody has a— now a good claim against
the original owner, he repossesses, he takes, he re-asserts his ownership.
Why can't the middleman be an absentee?
He could, but that's the reason
why— I understand.
So the גמרא sort of says, "Are you telling me people don't
buy property and turn it over within one night?" All right, fine.
But five years— okay, fine.
That's a good question. But the point is, if there is— if—
if ראובן Reuven is clearly a charlatan, right, or there's enough reason
to think he is, then my טענה ta'anah becomes a hollow claim.
All right?
First is preferring— legally preferring the legal force of possession over
ownership if you can't prove otherwise.
But the guy was never there.
Yeah, right.
But again, it's only a one day there, it's not a חזקה
chazakah. there, and it's just to make it that it's not— it
doesn't make us too worried that this guy's a total— is a
total thief, is a total charlatan.
But then you'd need to have somebody come forward and say, "Yeah,
I saw him there." Exactly, exactly.
He just had to be there one day. Okay, but yes, but
that's a good point. Even in the face— that's why this whole
thing is an issue. Because even in the face of חזקה, chazakah
I better be careful what I'm saying, because my חזקה only backs—
is only as good as the strength of my טענה. ta'anah. Okay?
But if my טענה ta'anah is "I bought it from so-and-so," and
there's a reason to think that, you know, that that's a reasonable
claim that so-and-so did buy it, and again, your silence in the
face of my חזקה, even without knowing for sure that ראובן Reuven
bought it, I would win. That's when you're known to be the
owner, I'm known to have a חזקה, and we're making a— and
the claim though is, "I bought it from a middleman" and nobody
exactly knows the story about the middleman. In this case, okay, that's
a classic case. In this case, okay, I don't have a חזקה
and you also don't have proof that you're the original owner. Okay,
so in this case, though, the reason that I lose, right, if
you don't have proof you're the original owner, why don't I just
say, "It's mine"? It's because in my claim that it's mine, I'm
implicitly admitting that originally it was yours, I bought it through so-and-so
who bought it from you— right, bought it from you? Since I'm
implicitly admitting that, and I don't have any proof that it's mine—
I don't have a חזקה and I don't have a שטר— then
I lose. Now the problem you all want to say is one
minute, whatever happened to like a מיגו migo or a הפה שאסר
peh she'assar or a הפה שהתיר? peh she'hitir? Why should my claim
when I concede it's yours, right, not also— if you're going to
believe me that it's yours, you should believe me that I bought
it? If it's not— so the answer is, we do believe you.
We believe you exactly what you said. You said you bought it
from ראובן, Reuven, and you don't know whether ראובן Reuven was the
original owner— was the legitimate owner. ראובן Reuven was— claimed he bought
it from you. So we totally believe you! You didn't have to
say anything! We totally accept your claim. So now we are saying,
you bought it from somebody who you have no evidence was a
legitimate owner. Okay? And you don't have adverse possession that gives evidence
that it wasn't, you know, that should be evidence that the original
owner no longer owns it. So what you're basically saying is, you
know, it's like the old joke, right, about like you bought the,
you know, the Brooklyn Bridge. Right? So it's like, you know, you
went to some guy, he claimed he owned the Brooklyn Bridge, you
know, you saying that you— that you bought it because you believed
him. שכוח. shkoiyach. Okay, but the original owner of the Brooklyn Bridge
still owns the Brooklyn Bridge. Why should they not own it anymore
just because you paid this guy money and you thought you were
buying it? Okay? So yes, you didn't have to say anything, but
based on your claim, your claim doesn't give you proof that it's
yours. It just proves that you went and you did a stupid
business deal. All right, so that's sort of the point here. Yes.
Well that makes sense if like the third guy is coming up
to the land of the original owner and saying, "This is mine
now, I bought it," and he's like, "What the heck?" But if
the third guy's on there let's say for a year... Right. ...for
a full year... he's there for a year and he's like been
living there and this random guy who hasn't been there...
Right. ...says, "I'm the original owner," ...owned it,
you know, that feels— it feels like who has the...
Right, so your point is like do— but is there any— there's
no like weight to something that's
like
partial?
Right, like that's our three years חזקה because we're comparing חזקה, the
two of them, the guy who's on this land.
Right, I understand. I mean, like הלכה halacha doesn't know about those
middle states, you know? I understand the point. So it is strange.
Like you say, like the whole thing, you're admitting, but the point
again is all you've admitted to is that you did a transaction
with somebody
who, you know, who claimed to be, who claimed to be an
owner. But, you know, but so what? Right? You know, why should
that make you own the property? Where's your evidence that it doesn't
belong to the original owner?
Yes, and something based on what that person claimed he got the
property from. Like, are we believing that middle person or not?
Well, if I, if I'm the one who's on it, say I
bought it from this guy and I know the guy got it
from you, then I'd be believed because then I'm claiming, but I'm
not saying that. I bought it from a guy who said he
bought it from
you. Eli, afterwards I'd like to sell you this nice building in
Rockefeller Center. I happen to be, I bought it from the owners
yesterday, right? So you're believing the third person based on his
words, based on his,
I
know, the, I understand what's troublesome is the original owner doesn't have
any evidence. The original owner is only known to be, right, that's
a good question
too. When שמעון Shimon concedes it belongs to the, I mean, whatever,
the buyer concedes it belongs to the original owner, is he conceding
that he knows it belongs to the original owner, or is he
conceding that I know it belongs to the original owner because that's
what, I assume, that's what he
said, then he didn't admit any, he didn't even admit the guy's
original ownership? No, I assume it means what I assume, this isn't
clear, but it's an excellent question. I assume if I'm the buyer
in this scenario, I forgot who I was, anyway, I assume I'm
saying like, yes, I know it was yours, but I bought it
from ראובן Reuven who told me he bought it from you. You're
right, if all, the only way I know it was yours was
that's what
ראובן Reuven claimed, then I haven't admitted anything. I assume what I'm
saying is yes, I know it's yours, but ראובן Reuven said he
bought it from you and I bought it from ראובן. Reuven. All
right, let's go on. All right, very complicated. That's why you have
these big רשב"ם. All right, moving on.
Why'd they buy it?
Yeah, that was pretty stupid of them. I understand. ההוא דאמר ליה
לחבריה, somebody says to his friend, מאי בעית בארעאי? Mai ba'it b'arai?
What are you doing in my land? אמר ליה, מפלניא זבינא, Mi-planya
zevina,
I bought it from Plonya, ואכלתיה שני חזקה, and I ate those
years of חזקה. אמר ליה, he said back to him, פלניא גזלנא
הוא, Planya gazlana hu, this Plonya is a גזלן. gazlan. Now, the
way the רשב"ם says it here, the way, I'll tell you the
way תוספות reads it. תוספות reads it that I have my three
years. Remember, I am believed with my three years when I say
I got it from some other person if that guy was there
for one day, right? If he was there for one day and
I say I assumed he was the owner, I was there three
years, you were silent in the face of three years, and I
bought it from him who claimed to be the owner and I'll
bring evidence that he was there for one day, so I would
be believed. Okay, but now the original owner says, that guy is
a known גזלן. gazlan. So what? So the הלכה halacha is a
known גזלן, gazlan, there's no חזקה for a גזלן gazlan because, you
know, the circumstances are interpreted differently. Okay, so he's making a claim
that says if it were true that that guy who sold it
to you was a known גזלן, gazlan, that would have undermined the
meaning of your חזקה.
Like we have professional גזלן. gazlan.
Exactly. Exactly. So the גמרא says, אמר ליה והא איכא סהדי דאתאי
אימלך בך ואמרת לי זיל זבין, Amar lei ve-ha ika sahadi d'atai
imlech bach v'amrat li zil zevin, one minute, I have witnesses that
I came to you and I said, you know, the guy there,
Mr. Fred גזלן, gazlan, is offering to sell me this land. What
do you think I should do? And you said to me, oh,
you should buy it. So the fact that you advised me to
buy it shows that he obviously didn't steal it from you because
then why would you be advising me to buy it? Okay, so,
oh well, no. So the גמרא says, so again, maybe a גזלן
gazlan doesn't have חזקה and so
on, but by your own advising me, that's proof that he was
a legitimate owner. So אמר ליה השני נוח לי הראשון קשה הימני,
Amar lei, hasheni noach li, harishon kasheh mimeni, yeah, I'd rather you
buy it because you are a nice honest guy, I'll take you
to court and I'll win the land back. If I would have
had to try to get it from
him, okay, the guy's a גזלן, gazlan, he's good at his job,
I would have had a hard time winning it back. Now, what
does this have to do with the whole עבירה aveirah of לפני
עור לא תתן מכשול, Lifnei Iver Lo Titen Michshol, which is about
giving bad advice to someone to serve your own self-interest? Okay, I
don't know. But apparently, okay, whether the guy did an עבירה aveirah
or not by giving him that advice, it's a reasonable claim. אמר
רבא Amar Rava דינא קאמר ליה, Dina ka'amar leh that actually is
a good response because people do give advice in order to serve
their own self-interest, believe it or not. כמאן, K'man, let's, the גמרא
says כמאן, k'man, like who? כמאן כדאדמון? K'man? K'Admon? תנן, Tnan, העורר
על השדה, ha-orer al ha-sadeh, I basically am challenging somebody's possession... possession
of my field, of what used to be my field. וחתם ליה
בעד *ve-chatam lei be-ed*, and the guy says, you can't say I
bought this illegitimately, you are a signed witness on my document. So
clearly you're implicitly conceding that I'm a legitimate owner of this field.
So אדמון *Admon* says, no, I can still say השני נוח לי
הראשון קשה ממנו *hasheni noach li harishon kasheh mimenu*. Sure I signed
the documents. I wanted you to take possession of it so because
you're an easier guy to bring to court than the first guy.
So my signing is not an admission. חכמים *Chachamim* say, איבד את
זכותו *ibad et zechuto*. Now as soon as I signed the document
I was clearly implicitly testifying that the guy was a legitimate owner.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, it sounds like this is exactly this
debate and you're going like אדמון *Admon*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
no, אפילו תימא רבנן *afilu teima rabanan*. Even the rabbis there who
say when you sign you lose your claim
here admit that when you give advice you don't lose your claim.
התם עביד ליה מעשה *hasam avid lei ma'aseh*. There when you actually
put your pen to paper and signed your name you are clearly
implicitly making a claim that this guy was the legitimate owner and
you can't say it was just a way, a strategy. הכא דיבורא
*hacha dibura*. Here you're just talking. Okay, עביד איניש דמקרי ואמר *avid
inish de-mikrei ve-amar*. People give advice even if they're, even if and
they're not without really conceding. So I gave advice which was serving
my best interest and it doesn't prove that I am not the
legitimate owner. It's really troubling though given that this is like a
classic like לפני עיוור *lifnei iver*. But I mean maybe the point
still is that the guy gets reimbursed. But anyway, so with that
we'll end with that now and we will pick up with a
similar story tomorrow.
Have a beautiful day.
Well, the next is categorized...